Comic book collection on medical themes
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
- True adventure comic books of the 1940s, 1941-1948; Series I
  - Science Comics, 1946
    - Science Comics, No. 1, 1946 January (Box 2, Folder 15)
      "White Magic: The Miracle of Penicillin," [9-15]. "Story of the accidental discovery of penicillin by Alexander Fleming, with much attention to his lab work as well as that of the later scientists; learning how to cultivate it; finding stronger strains; cranking up industrial production; includes Robert Coghill, Stuart Craddock, Howard Florey, Norman Heatley, Frederick Ridley, Charles Thorn." BH
    - Science Comics, No. 2, 1946 March (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Rudy Palais (artist), "Walter Reed: The Man Who Conquered Yellow Fever," [26-31]. "Famous experiments on yellow fever conducted in Cuba in 1900." Story similar to versions in True Comics, No. 1, and in Real Life Comics, No. 19, "but this version has excellent, highly dramatic art by Rudy Palais; more emphasis here on the scientific puzzles and less on the grotesque aspects; includes Agramonte, Carroll, Finlay, Kissinger, Lazear, Moran." BH
    - Science Comics, No. 3, 1946 May (Box 2, Folder 17)
      "The Conquest of Pain," 23-27. "How dentist Horace Wells recognized that laughing gas, nitrous oxide, could offer painless dentistry and surgery; success in 1844; failure in 1846; ether mentioned at end as if it were just a minor refinement of this technique." BH
    - Science Comics, No. 4, 1946 July (Box 2, Folder 18)
      "Blood Plasma," (24-27]. "Story about technology in use in blood banks, with no attention to discovery; factual material supplied by Sharpe and Dohme; of medical advances made during the war 'perhaps none was so important in the saving of human lives' as blood plasma." BH
    - Science Comics, No. 5, 1946 September (Box 2, Folder 19)
      "Theobald Smith and Texas Fever," [17-23]. "Smith's passion for medical microbiology; main subject his inventive experimental work for US government that showed ticks were the source of all Texas cattle fever; results aided in solving yellow fever; 'greatest of all American microbe hunters.'" BH
  - Trail Blazers, 1942
    Trail Blazers was published in 4 issues, 1941-1942 October, by Street & Smith Publications, Inc., New York.
    - Trail Blazers, No. 4, 1942 October (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Gary Gray (artist), "Louis Pasteur," [11-19]. "Detailed biography, possibly patterned after 1936 movie." BH
  - True Animal Picture Stories, 1947
    True Animal Picture-Stories was published in 2 issues, both in 1947, by the Parents' Institute, Inc., Chicago.
    - True Animal Picture Stories, No. 2, 1947 Spring (Box 2, Folder 21)
      "Friend of Animals," [28-29]. "Non-cartoon story (text with one illustration); nothing directly medical in this biography of Henry Bergh, the founder of the American Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals; notable for omitting his significant opposition to medical experiments using animals." Similar to story in True Comics, No. 16. Issue date taken from index; cover says "Summer." BH
  - True Comics, 1941-1947
    True Comics (84 issues, 1941 April 1941 - 1950 August) New York: The Parents' Institute, Inc.; then Chicago: The Parents Magazine Press; then, beginning with issue 29, Chicago: True Comics, Inc.
    The motto of True Comics was: "TRUTH is stranger and a thousand times more thrilling than FICTION."
    - True Comics, No. 1, 1941 April (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Two copies. Second copy has some separated pages and no cover.
      "Yellow Jack," 37-43. "Discovery and proof that mosquitoes transmit yellow fever; much on human experiments including fatalities; featuring doctors Agramonte, Carroll, Lazear (who dies a martyr to science), Finlay and Reed, and volunteer subjects, Kissenger (Kissinger) and Moran." BH
    - True Comics, No. 2, 1941 June (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Covers separate from body of comic book.
      William B. Everett (artist), "The Story of the Red Cross," 46-52. "Establishment of the International Red Cross, featuring Jean Henri Dunant and Florence Nightingale." BH
    - True Comics, No. 3, 1941 August (Box 3, Folder 3)
      "Death Fighter: Dr. Robert Koch," 12-19. "Biography with focus on his medical microbiology research: anthrax, solid culture media, microphotography, cholera, the Nobel Prize." BH
    - True Comics, No. 4, 1941 September (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Cover of comic book separate from text. "Danger in the Arctic: Joe Crosson, Aviator," 12-21. "Primarily a story of pioneering aviation in Alaska, but it also includes a life-saving delivery of 'scarlet fever-serum' to save children's lives; other sources say the serum was for diphtheria." BH
    - True Comics, No. 10, 1942 March (Box 3, Folder 5)
      AI Pagaly [or Pagal?] (artist), "Adrift on an Ice Pan," 26-31. "Dramatic survival story of missionary Dr. Wilfred Grenfell in Newfoundland, lost on floating ice in an attempt to visit an isolated patient; wilderness skills brought him through, partly by his sacrificing some of his sled dogs; was well-known author." BH
    - True Comics, No. 15, 1942 August (Box 3, Folder 6)
      "The Discoverer of Hidden Hunger," 37-41. "Christian Eijkman of Holland, experimenting in Java on animals and prisoners, showed that beri-beri was due to lack of vitamins in polished rice; Nobel Prize." BH
    - True Comics, No. 16, 1942 September (Box 3, Folder 7)
      "Friend of Animals: Henry Bergh," 22-27. "Nothing directly medical in this story of the founder of the American Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals; story notable for omitting his significant opposition to medical experiments using animals." BH
      "Cave Nurse," 33-35. "Londoner Joanna Stavridi, heroic war nurse in Crete working for Red Cross, treating Nazi as well as Allied wounded." BH
      "The Modest Miracle: Robert Williams," 49-53. "American chemist in the Philippines discovers character of Vitamin B1 and how to manufacture it and put it into food to prevent beri-beri." BH
    - True Comics, No. 19, 1942 December (Box 3, Folder 8)
      "From Brooklyn to Bataan: Anny Nurse Helen Summers," 22-27. "Helen Summers and her sister nurses of bombed Bataan -- brave under fire, loyal unto death -- are America's sweethearts of 1942." Quoted by BH.
      "Conqueror of the White Plague: Dr. Edward Trudeau," 54-59. "Biography of the doctor who made the outdoor cure for tuberculosis famous in America with his Saranac Lake sanatorium; story gives much attention to a rabbit experiment by which he showed the disease required both germs and inadequate food and rest." BH
    - True Comics, No. 21, 1943 February (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Two copies. "The Doctor Who Came Back: Dr. Samuel Mudd," 36-41. "Mudd provided treatment to Lincoln's assassin before Booth was identified as such; yet he was jailed; while in prison, he volunteered to care for guards and soldiers in an epidemic; given a pardon for this heroic service." BH
    - True Comics, No. 24, 1943 May-June (Box 3, Folder 10)
      "Canada's Pioneer Nurse: Jeanne Mance," [15-18). "Biography of 17th-century French settler who cared for others during Indian attacks; helped found city of Montreal and its hospital, the Hotel Dieu." BH
    - True Comics, No. 25, 1943 July (Box 3, Folder 11)
      "The Mayo Family: Medicine's Miracle Men [Part 1]," [8-12]. "Biography of country doctor William Mayo, going to NYC for advanced training in the new scientific medicine and bringing it back to Minnesota with great success." BH
    - True Comics, No. 26, 1943 August (Box 3, Folder 12)
      "The Mayo Family: Medicine's Miracle Men, Part 2," [18-22]. "Story of two sons of William Mayo, trained first by their father; they establish the famous clinic, treat thousands of patients, and fund a graduate medical school at the University of Minnesota." BH
    - True Comics, No. 30, 1943 December (Box 3, Folder 13)
      "Norman Bethune," [14-19]. Biography of Canadian physician who developed mobile units to provide blood plasma on battlefields in the Spanish Civil War, and then went on to provide medical care in China, where he died doing surgery." BH
    - True Comics, No. 31, 1944 January (Box 3, Folder 14)
      "First Lady of the Army Medical Corps: Mary Walker," [30-33]. "Biography of Dr. Mary Walker emphasizing the discrimination she faced, her substantial medical service in the Civil War, and her work for dress reform and women's causes." BH
    - True Comics, No. 32, 1944 February (Box 3, Folder 15)
      "The Fight Against Infantile Paralysis," [26-29]. "Presentation of the history and facts of polio as told by a soldier who had recovered from his childhood case, Philip Hawco; explained earlier epidemics, FDR's and celebrities' role in raising funds for care and research, the Kenny treatment." BH
    - True Comics, No. 33, 1944 March (Box 3, Folder 16)
      "Common Sense about the Common Cold," [16-19]. Not historical. "Joe Smith" takes precautions against the common cold and when he gets a sore throat, he stays home, rests, and drinks lots of liquids.
      "Call Him 'Doc,'" [30-34]. "Story of hospital janitor Jim Bay, who became a battlefield medic in New Guinea jungles; use of sulfa drug for wounds; called "Doc" for saving many lives." BH "Hit the Silk," [41-47]. "Capt. Frank P. Bender, an aviator downed in New Guinea jungle survived with quinine pills for malaria and sulfa drugs for wounds until carried to the base by friendly natives." BH
    - True Comics, No. 34, 1944 April (Box 3, Folder 17)
      "The Doctor Declares War!" [1-6]. "Story has little medical content; American Dr. Gordon S. Seagrave was in Burma as a missionary, when that country was attacked by the Japanese; eventually he and colleagues evacuated to India, where they prepared to return to Burma." BH
      "Angel of the Battlefield,"[16-22]. "Biography of Clara Barton with emphasis on childhood and Civil War service, with only last panel mentioning the Red Cross." BH
    - True Comics, No. 38, 1944 August (Box 3, Folder 18)
      "Oregon Trail Blazer: Marcus Whitman," [15-18]. "Medical missionary to Oregon territory 'to bring Christianity and medical science,' though story includes only modest amount of medical care and no science; at the end he and his wife are slaughtered by Indians." BH
      "One-Woman Army: Lt. Annie Den Hooch," [26-30]. "Dutch nurse who resists Nazi occupation, then escapes to England to help Dutch army there; first woman to enter Dutch army; though she wears white uniform and is in medical settings, her heroism is military, not medical." BH
    - True Comics, No. 41, 1944 December (Box 3, Folder 19)
      "Penicillin," [18-22]. "Very new drug in 1944; early discovery by Dr. Alexander Fleming; new work by Dr. Howard Florey (his colleague Ernest Chain not mentioned); industrial-scale production in US; used when hundreds burned in Boston nightclub fire; news coverage of first patients." BH
      "WAC Under Fire!" [30-32]. "Story about Sgt. Jean Young, a hospital staff member who risked attack to bring a wounded soldier back to her hospital." BH
      "Ski Patrol," [34-36]. "Volunteers turned their peace-time sport into a war-time service, including rescue of downed plane crews." BH
      "Desperate Message," [43-47]. "Story of Marine Corporal Walter Bodt, on Guadalcanal, who risked exposure to enemy fire by doing improvised semaphore signaling to warn his comrades of danger; he was hit, but survived; story's only medical relevance was use of blood plasma." BH
    - True Comics, No. 48, 1946 April (Box 3, Folder 20)
      "Hero Without a Gun," [1 -5]. "Story of a member of the medical corps, Pfc. Desmond Doss, a Seventh Day Adventist who refused to carry a gun; many acts of heroism under fire; Congressional Medal of Honor presented by President Truman on 12 October 1945; no explicit medical content." BH
    - True Comics, No. 51, 1946 August (Box 4, Folder 1)
      "Miracle Against Pain," [26-30]. "Biography of William Morton, from childhood experiments through the great triumph of ether surgery in 1846 at the Massachusetts General Hospital; C. T. Jackson and Horace Wells included; painless surgery proclaimed 'the most important discovery of the nineteenth century.'" BH
    - True Comics, No. 52, 1946 September (Box 4, Folder 2)
      "Doctor Facts," [1-5]. "Biography of Bernard Baruch, statesman and adviser to presidents; noted as son of a poor Jewish doctor; medical significance is his advocacy of funding for medical research, especially to help returning veterans, and his own million-dollar gift for that purpose." BH
      Folder also includes a much later reprint of "Dr. Facts," "A Special Historical Comic Book Reprint to share with Baruch College alumni and friends." Has commentary on the inside front cover by Bert Hansen.
    - True Comics, No. 53, 1946 October (Box 4, Folder 3)
      "Chick Doctor," [36-37]. "Describing Doris Mae Gnauck as an 18 year old, story covers her earlier years, ending with her majoring in poultry husbandry and biochemistry at the University of Wisconsin; from 'childhood hobby of helping sick chicks' to 'the wizard of chickenology.'" BH
    - True Comics, No. 59, 1947 April (Box 4, Folder 4)
      "Queer Cures," [24-25]. "Traditional Chinese medicines; text neutral, but title and some words like 'cling' and 'supposedly' have hostile tone; 'China has made many discoveries, but many Chinese still cling to their ancient belief in medicine made from animals' bodies.'" BH
- Later comics on health themes, 1951-1997; Series II
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Comic books in this series were donated by William Helfand.
  - Comics on drugs and addictions, Subseries 1
    - Cocaine Comix, No. 1, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Published in 4 issues, 1975-1982, by Last Gasp, San Francisco. Last Gasp (short for Last Gasp Eco Funnies) was a company created by Richard Corben. Cocaine Comix was an underground series for adults containing humorous stories about cartoonish cocaine users.
    - Cocaine Comix, No. 2, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Cocaine Comix, No. 4, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Mary Wings, Are Your Highs Getting You Down?, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      By Mary Wings "and women in the substance abuse groups at the Pacific Center, Berkeley, California." Stories are about the recovery of a woman alcoholic and of a woman addicted to marijuana. Published by Last Gasp Comix, San Francisco.
    - Captain America Goes to War Against Drugs (Box 4, Folder 9)
      "Produced in cooperation with the Federal Bureau of Investigation and the New York State Association of Life Underwriters." Published by Marvel Comics, New York. Issue contains a single story about Mitch, a pitcher on the high school baseball team, who is offered drugs by an evil space alien disguised as a human. Mitch is saved from addiction and bullying by the intervention of Captain America. List of agencies that can help those with drug problems on the inside back cover.
  - Comics on other public health issues, Subseries 2
    - Dennis the Menace Takes a Poke at Poison, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      "Prepared in cooperation of the Food and Drug Administration and the Public Health Service, U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare. Copyright 1961 by Hall Syndicate, Inc. Dennis sprays weed killer on Mr. Wilson. Public health message about household poisons.
    - The Asthma Warriors, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      By Michelle Livingston (writer), Alton D. Wilson (artist), and others. Copyright 1997 by Mount Sinai Medical Center. Science fiction story about Asthmodeus coming to earth from a galaxy far away. Public health message on controlling asthma.
  - Comics advertising a health product, Subseries 3
    - Major Inapak: The Space Age, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Comic book was published by Magazine Enterprises, New York, c. 1951. The inside covers and the back cover advertise Inapak, a chocolate-flavored health drink with 11 vitamins and 9 minerals. The science fiction adventure story, illustrated by Bob Powell, was set in 2031. It told of Major Inapak's rocket voyage to the moon in the 1980s along with an orphan boy Robin who had stowed himself in the rocket. They battled aliens on the moon, and brought back to earth a friendly alien. At the end of the story, the reader learns that Robin is the narrator.
- Supplement 2017, Series III
  Additional comics donated by Bert Hansen in 2017. A few comics on public health themes donated by William Helfand were also added to the Supplement.
  - Additional true adventure comic books of the 1940s, 1942-1949; Subseries 1
    - Negro Heroes, No. 1, 1947 March (Box 4, Folder 13)
      Published by the National Urban League with permission of Parents Institute, the publishers of True Comics, Real Comics, and Calling All Girls. There were only two issues of this rare title. This issue contains an article on George Washington Carver titled "Wizard of Science." It is the same story as found in True Comics, No. 18. See below.
    - Negro Heroes, No. 2, 1948 Summer (Box 4, Folder 14)
      This second issue was published by the Urban League in cooperation with Delta Sigma Theta Sorority. Includes "Dynamic Fighter: Mabel K. Staupers" [25-28}. BH: Staupers was a "pioneering Negro nurse, who organized aggressively for major social and institutional changes in and out of medicine; succeeded, especially in Harlem medical care and in gaining a place for Negro nurses in the armed forces; pictured with Eleanor Roosevelt." Featured article in this issue is about Jackie Robinson.
    - Topix, vol. 8, No. 9, 1949 November 14 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      Published by the Catechetical Guild Educational Society, St. Paul, Minnesota. A Roman Catholic comic to be used for education. Contains "Microbe Mystery," [9-14] on the 18th century microbe experimenter Lazarro Spallanzani who was also a Catholic priest.
    - Trail Blazers, Vol. 1, No. 3, 1942 October (Box 4, Folder 16)
      No medical stories but Bert Hansen notes that there is a story by "Jack Gordon Farr" which looks like the style of the Pasteur story in No. 4 drawn by "Gary Gray." See Box 2, Folder 20.
    - True Animal Picture Stories, No. 1, 1947 Winter (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Contains "Balto of Nome," pp. 1-3, ending with the erecting of a bronze sculpture of Balto in Central Park.
    - True Comics, No. 18, 1943 October (Box 4, Folder 18)
      Includes a story about George Washington Carver, titled "Wizard of Science." Carver, the son of slaves, had recently died in January 1943.
  - Later comic book stories about medical history, 1952-2003; Subseries 2
    - Classics Illustrated, No. 138A: Adventures in Science, 1957 June (Box 4, Folder 19)
      Published by Gilberton Company, Inc. New York. "The Discoveries of Louis Pasteur," pp. 45-66. BH: Same story as in Picture Progress, November 1954. See Box 4, Folder 23.
    - Dr. Kildare, No. 2, 1962 July-September (Box 4, Folder 20)
      Dell Comics, published by Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer, Inc. There is a story about Louis Pasteur on the inside front cover and other medical history bits on the inside back cover. Subtitle of issue is: "Dr. Kildare battles a dread disease in a desperate struggle for a man's life." The story is about Dr. Kildare bringing a young doctor from China, an expert on a rare disease ("DOX") who saves the patient's life and overcomes ethnic prejudice.
    - For Boys Only, vol. 1, No. 2, 1953 September (Box 4, Folder 21)
      "The Magazine for Boys of All Ages." Published by Baily Enterprises, New York. Digest size. Gives month as October on the cover. In addition to fictional stories, there are historical stories including "Laennac [Laennec]: Inventor of the Stethoscope," pp. 52-55.
    - New Heroic Comics, No. 72, 1952 May (Box 4, Folder 22)
      Contains "Broken Glass" [27-28], a story about Dean Shore, a 22-year-old medical student at Jefferson Medical College, who saved a workman who had fallen onto a pile of broken glass.
    - Picture Progress, Vol. 2, No. 3, 1954 November (Box 4, Folder 23)
      Published by the Gilberton Company, Inc., New York. An educational comic with many advisors. Entire issue is on Pasteur including a quiz and a game. Main story is "The Discoveries of Louis Pasteur," pp. 1-22.
    - SPX 2002 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Published by the Comic Book Legal Defense Fund, Northampton, Mass. Stories, many of which are true stories, are by various authors. The medical history stories are Diana Tamblyn, "Duty Must Be Done: The Story of Frederick Banting" [10-19], and Joyce Brabner (writer) and Josh Neufield (artist), "Typhoid Mary" (4p.).
    - SPX 2003 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      The story "1918" (pp. 14-23) by Ken Boesem is about the influenza epidemic of 1918.
    - Treasure Chest of Fun and Fact, vol. 24, No. 10, 1963 January 23 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Published by George A. Pflaum, Inc., Dayton, Ohio. Contains Felix G. Arnstein (writer) and R. Crandall (artist), "Man Against Disease: The Story of Louis Pasteur," pp. 26-31.
    - Wonder Woman, No. 4, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Published by National Comics Publications, Inc., New York. Several issues contain a short feature, "Wonder Women of History." This issue has "Florence Sabin (Wonder Women of History)," [20].
    - The World Around Us: The Illustrated Story of Dogs, 1958 September (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Published by Gilberton World-Wide Publications, Inc., New York. Story on Balto (Heroic Dogs), [5-11].
    - The World Around Us: The Illustrated Story of Great Scientists, 1960 February (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Published by Gilberton World-Wide Publications, Inc., New York. Three stories on medical history: "The Body is Charted" [7-11] about Andreas Vesalius with two pages identifying other historical figures; "Germs Cause Disease" [31-36} about Pasteur; and "The Inner Man" [60-67] about Freud with two pages identifying other psychologists and psychiatrists.
    - The World Around Us, No. 36, Fight for Life, 1961 October (Box 5, Folder 7)
      Published by Gilberton World-Wide Publications, Inc., New York. Includes 16 medical history stories, about 3/4 of the issue.
  - Public health themes, 1951-1990; Subseries 3
    - Chic Young's Blondie, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Copyright by King Features Syndicate. Inc. Produced by Joe Musial, and published by the New York State Department of Mental Hygiene. BH: "These were public service comic books designed to help people overcome their negative feelings about mental illness and psychiatry. This book and the next are originals from the NYS Department, but the books were widely reprinted by government agencies in other states for many years." Message from Newton Bigelow, M.D., Commissioner of Mental Health, State of New York on inside back cover. Stories are: "Scapegoat," "Love Conquers All," "Let's Face It," and "On Your Own."
    - Chic Young's Blondie, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Copyright by King Features Syndicate, Inc. Adapted by Joe Musial. Produced by the New York State Department of Mental Hygiene. Message from the Commissioner of Mental Health, Paul H. Koch, M.D., on inside back cover. Stories are: "Chain Reaction!," "Hurray for Love," "Face the Music!," and "To Each His Own." Though titles have changed, the stories are updated versions of the 1951 stories.
    - The Fight to Save America's Waters: A Mark Trail Adventure in Public Health and Conservation >, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Separated Materials
      Published by the U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, Public Health Service, Division of Water Supply and Pollution Control.
    - Strip AIDS U.S.A.: A Collection of Cartoon Art to Benefit People with AIDS, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Edited by Trina Robbins, Bill Sienkiewicz, and Robert Triplow, Published by Last Gasp, San Francisco. On safe sex, prejudice, government inaction, etc.